A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF), Media, Arts, and Culture (MAC), Office Files of Orlando Bagwell FA1728
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF), Media, Arts, and Culture (MAC), Office Files of Orlando Bagwell
2000-2006
Rockefeller Archive Center
Bagwell, Orlando
Ford Foundation
FA1728
.76 Cubic Feet 2 Hollinger boxes
Arrangement
Collection consists of one series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject files, 2000-2006
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:183.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the office files Orlando Bagwell created when he worked as a Program Officer in the Media, Arts, and Culture Unit (MAC) of the Ford Foundation's Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF). It consists of one series of subject files. These files document the activities Bagwell performed when carrying out his responsibilities for managing a grant portfolio focused on public media and media rights and access and for leading the Foundation's five-year Global Perspectives in a Digital Age: Transforming Public Service Media initiative. Some of the files in the series were inherited from Bagwell's MAC predecessors.
Common types of documents found throughout the collection include correspondence, memos, drafts, reports, proposals, concept papers, notes, film treatments, summaries, articles, abstracts, biographies, promotional materials, and publications. There is also one video tape.
Grantees discussed within the files received support for producing films about race and inequality in America, advancing the representation of Latino Americans in film and TV, strengthening and innovating public media, and assisting the Ford Foundation's Global Perspectives in a Digital Age: Transforming Public Service Media initiative.
Biographical / Historical
Orlando Bagwell is a filmmaker and former Program Officer at the Ford Foundation. During his time at the Ford Foundation, he led the Foundation's five-year Global Perspectives in a Digital Age: Transforming Public Service Media initiative and then co-founded the Foundation's JustFilms initiative in 2010.
The first part of Bagwell's career was centered in Boston, Massachusetts. He produced for WGBH and founded ROJA Productions there.
Bagwell joined the Ford Foundation in 2004 as a Program Officer in the Media, Arts, and Culture Unit (MAC) of the Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF). Within this position, Bagwell was responsible for managing a grant portfolio focused on public media and media rights and access. The JustFilms initiative that he helped establish in 2010 provides funding to documentary filmmakers focused on social justice storytelling and has supported films like How to Survive a Plague. Bagwell left the Ford Foundation in 2013.
In 2014, Bagwell became the director of the documentary program at the University of California Berkeley's Graduate School of Journalism. He continues to produce documentaries.
Bagwell earned a B.S. in film and then an M.A. in broadcast journalism from Boston University. Documentaries he has produced and or directed include Eyes on the Prize, Africans in America: America's Journey through Slavery, and episodes of American Experience such as Malcom X: Make It Plain and Citizen King.
Ford Foundation; African Americans -- Social conditions; Digital media; Documentary films; Freedom of expression; Hispanic Americans in mass media; Public television; Race; Racism
- Subject files, 2000-2006; 1; .76 Cubic Feet About 2 LTR size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains the subject files Orlando Bagwell created when he worked as a Program Officer in the Media, Arts, and Culture Unit (MAC) of the Ford Foundation's Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF). Files regard the Foundation's support of grantees like California Newsreel, WGBH, and the National Hispanic Foundation for the Arts (NHFA). These organizations received funding for producing films on race and inequality in America, strengthening and innovating public media, and advancing the representation of Latino Americans in film and television. The files also provide evidence of some of the Foundation's self-directed projects regarding public service media and freedom of expression such as the Global Perspectives in a Digital Age: Transforming Public Service Media initiative and the Stone Soup (Ford Foundation Freedom of Expression Working Group) meetings. Some materials in the series were inherited from past MAC Program Officers like Jon Santos because the projects those records concerned were passed on to Bagwell.
  Subject files regarding MAC's support of the California Newsreel film series Hidden Epidemic and RACE: The Power of an Illusion contain a significant amount of records such as film summaries and press articles related to the promotion of the series. There are also drafts of films treatments. Other type of materials found throughout the series include correspondence, memos, reports, proposals, concept papers, notes, abstracts, biographies, and publications.
  - California Newsreel, Hidden Epidemic, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - California Newsreel, Hidden Epidemic, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hidden Epidemic scholar - Dolores Acevedo-Garcia, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hidden Epidemic scholar - Nancy Adler, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hidden Epidemic scholar - Troy Duster, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hidden Epidemic scholar - Harold Freedman, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hidden Epidemic scholar - Camara Jones, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hidden Epidemic scholar - Ichiro Kawachi, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Beloved Community Center of Greensboro (BCC) proposal, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hidden Epidemic scholar - Brian Smedley, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hidden Epidemic scholar - S. Leonard Syme, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hidden Epidemic scholar - Makani Themba-Nixon, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hidden Epidemic scholar - David Williams, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - California Newsreel, Hidden Epidemic, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Nonprofit Finance Fund (NFF), 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - WGBH, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - WGBH Digitial Media Investment Fund (DMI), 2006 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - California Newsreel, RACE: The Power of an Illusion - Press kit, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - California Newsreel, RACE: The Power of an Illusion - Narrative and financial report and press, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - California Newsreel, RACE: The Power of an Illusion - Promotion, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - California Newsreel, RACE: The Power of an Illusion, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - California Newsreel, RACE: The Power of an Illusion - Promotional materials, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Stone Soup (Ford Foundation Freedom of Expression Working Group), 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - National Hispanic Foundation for the Arts (NHFA), 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
    - National Hispanic Foundation for the Arts (NHFA): Promoting Latino talent both in front of and behind the camera, undated; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11191)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
      Video submitted as part of the National Hispanic Foundation for the Arts' (NHFA) final grant report to the Ford Foundation.